<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise declaring, and confirming against all obiections the just title and right of the moste excellent and worthie prince, Iames the sixt, King of Scotland, to the succession of the croun of England. Whereunto is added a discourse shewing how necessarie it is for the realme of England, that he be in due time acknowledged and admitted to the succession of the kingdome.</title>
            <author>Philodikaios, Irenicus.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1599</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 68 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B00559</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19881.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S94721</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52633329</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52633329</idno>
            <idno type="VID">174758</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B00559)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 174758)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2124:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise declaring, and confirming against all obiections the just title and right of the moste excellent and worthie prince, Iames the sixt, King of Scotland, to the succession of the croun of England. Whereunto is added a discourse shewing how necessarie it is for the realme of England, that he be in due time acknowledged and admitted to the succession of the kingdome.</title>
                  <author>Philodikaios, Irenicus.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[45] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. Waldegrave,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1599]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Anonymous. Preface signed: Irenicus Philodikaios (a pseudonym).</note>
                  <note>Imprint information from STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signed in Waldegrave's normal fashion.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [A]-E⁴, F³ (last leaf blank?).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Trinity College (Dublin, Ireland). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>James --  I, --  King of England, 1566-1625 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Kings and rulers --  Succession --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  Politics and government --  16th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  Foreign relations --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England --  Foreign relations --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1558-1603 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:174758:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:174758:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A TREATISE</hi> DECLARING, AND confirming againſt all obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions the juſt title and right of the moſte excellent and worthie Prince, IAMES the ſixt, King of Scotland, to the ſucceſſion of the croun of England.</p>
            <p>WHEREVNTO IS ADDED A DISCOVRSE Shewing how neceſſarie it is for the Realme of England, that he be in due time acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged and admitted to the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:174758:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:174758:2"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>SEING the great diuerſitie of opinions, which is found in men of all Eſtates throughout this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme, concerning the Royall ſucceſſion, and fore-ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the manifeſt danger of ciuill and forraine warres which thence are lyke to enſue, to the notable hurte and domage, if not to the vtter ruine of this noble Kingdome; except the ſubjects thereof bee in due time rightlie informed to whom by right the croun falleth, next after her Maieſtie: I thought it my du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, being a member of one bodie with them trulie to informe ſo manie of them, as I might, concerning this matter, by publiſhing this treatiſe; wherein the right of the next lawfull ſucceſſour is declared, and confirmed againſt all obiections. And for that I know it to be the opinion of ſundry men, that in this preſent controuerſie it is not onlie to be conſidered, to whom by right the croune appertaineth; but alſo whether his admiſſion may be auailable or hurtfull to the common wealth: I thought good to adde to the ſaide declaration, &amp; defence of his right, a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe ſhewing howe neceſſarie and expedient it is for the common wealth, that hee be in due time ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged and admitted to the ſucceſſion of this Kingdome. Both which parts I haue brieflie hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, thinking it ynough to proue and confirme them with a competent number of weighty and forceable arguments, the rather for that the former part hath beene more at length declared and confirmed by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in treatiſes alreadie publiſhed: and the other
<pb facs="tcp:174758:3"/>
point is of it ſelf ſo cleare and manifeſt, as fewer rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons than I alledge may be ſufficient for the certain proofe and euidencie therof. I hope, that you (my deare countrie-men) for whoſe inſtruction and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoofe I haue publiſhed this little pamphlet, will thankfully accept this my good meaning and honeſt endeuour, making your profite therof by embtacing and furthering ſo iuſte and honorable a cauſe, as is heere recommended vnto you, and procuring there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by (together with your owne ſafetie and advantage) the peace, honour, &amp; proſperitie of this your natiue countrie. With which happie fore-ſight beſeeching God to indue you, I hartilie bid you fare-well.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>IRENICVS PHILODIKAIOS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:174758:3"/>
            <head>The right of the King of Scotland by deſcent of kindred is declared.</head>
            <p>BEing to declare who by all right is next to our ſoueraigne Ladie, Queen Elizabeth, in the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of the kingdom, I thought it needeles to draw the deſcent of ſuch, as with anie reaſon or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babilitie may after her Maieſties deceaſe lay claime to the croun, further of, than from the vnion of the houſes of Lancaſter, and York, in the perſons of the moſt renowmed King Henrie the ſeauenth, and of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizabeth, eldeſt daughter to King Edward the fourth, right and lawfull heires of both the Royall families.</p>
            <p>For, as for the Erle of Huntington, and others de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended from George Duke of Clarence, youngeſt brother to King Edward the fourth, they may not juſtlie be greeued, if they be placed in rank after ſuch as are lawfullie deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded from the heire of their own houſe of York, joyned in mariage to the head of the familie of Lancaſter.</p>
            <p>And as for the king of Spaine, and his ſiſter the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanta, for whome farre ſought titles haue beene for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by ſome fugitiue Perſons of our own nation, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring for the alteration of Religion, to make this flou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riſhing common wealth a praie to the enemies ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; I am perſwaded there is none, that hath the hart of a true ſubiect, or naturall Engliſh-man, how ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer hee bee affected in Religion, that will not vtterlie abhorre and deteſt the defending, or approouing of anie ſuch titles, tending to the great diſhonour and
<pb facs="tcp:174758:4"/>
vtter ſubuerſion of this Realm, and to the notable diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace of ſo manie worthie Princes, as ſince the time of King Henrie the ſixt hitherto therin haue reigned. But deſiſting from the mention of titles no les falſe, than odious, I come to the orderlie deſcent of Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie the ſeuenths progenie.</p>
            <p>King Henrie, the ſeuenth of that name, had iſſue by Queene Elizabeth, beſides Prince Arthur, and an other, who deceaſed without ſucceſſion, Prince Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, Ladie Margaret, and Ladie Marie.</p>
            <p>King Henrie the eight, who ſucceeded to his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, had iſſue King Edward, Queene Marie, and Queene Elizabeth now reigning.</p>
            <p>Ladie Margaret, eldeſt daughter to King Henrie the ſeauenth, was maried to Iames the fourth, King of Scotland, who begat on her Iames the fift, father to Marie Queen of Scotland, &amp; Douagier of France: whoſe onlie ſonne and heire is King Iames the ſixt, who at this preſent reigneth, and hath alreadie iſſue Prince Henrie, Ladie Elizabeth, and another daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. The ſaid Queen Margaret, after the death of King Iames the fourth, was maried to Archibald Earle of Angus, and by him had a daughter called the Ladie Margaret Dowglaſſe, which was wife to Mathew Stewart Earle of Lenox: by whome ſhee had two ſonnes, Henrie Lord Darlie, and Charles: whereof Henrie beeing the elder was ioyned in mariage to Marie Queen of Scotland, and of her begat the king that now is: And Charles, the younger brother, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried Elizabeth, the daughter of Sir William Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh; by whome he had one only daughter yet liuing, named the Ladie Arbella.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:174758:4"/>Marie, the younger daughter of King Henrie the ſeuenth, after the deceaſe of her firſt husband, Lewes the twelth, King of France, by whome ſhee had no iſſue, was maried to Charles Brandon Duke of Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folke, by whome ſhe had two daughters, Ladie Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Ladie Eleonor.</p>
            <p>The Ladie Frances was maried to Henrie Gray, Marques of Dorceſter, afterward Duke of Suffolke: who begat of her three daughters, Iane, Katherine, and Marie.</p>
            <p>The eldeſt of them, Ladie Iane, was maried to Gilford Duldey, the ſonne of Iohn Duke of Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>berland, of whom ſhe had no iſſue, being ſone af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter her mariage put to death by Queene Marie, for taking on her the croun. Ladie Catherine firſt eſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to Henrie Harbert, eldeſt ſonne of William Erle of Pembroke, this contract being diſſolued, had by the Earle of Hartford, after a priuie contract made betwixt them, as they both alledged, the Lord Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>champ, and his brother, who are yet liuing. Ladie Marie the youngeſt, who was betrouthed to Arthur Lord Gray of Wilton, died without iſſue.</p>
            <p>Ladie Eleonor, the ſecond daughter of Ladie Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Ducheſſe of Suffolke, was maried to Henrie Clif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, Erle of Cumberland: who had by her a daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter named Margaret, that was married to Henrie Stanley, Erle of Darbie: by whome ſhee had iſſue Fernande, William, and Frances.</p>
            <p>This is the orderlie ſucceſſion of ſuch as are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended from the vnion of both the Royall families of York, and Lancaſter: whereby it is euident, that the iſſue of King Henrie the eight failing in our ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne
<pb facs="tcp:174758:5"/>
Ladie, Queene Elizabeth, the right of the croune by deſcent of blood falleth vppon IAMES the ſixt, King of Scotland, by lineall ſucceſſion heire to the Ladie Margaret, eldeſt daughter of King Henrie the ſeauenth, aſwell of his fathers ſide, as of his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. The truth whereof being ſo manifeſt, as it can not be denied, ſome fauorers of the houſe of Suffolk, and others alledge certain impediments to debarre him from his right. If I would followe the example of others, and eſpeciallie of ſuch as maintaine the falſe titles of the King of Spaine, &amp; his ſiſter, I might alledge impediments of no little importance againſt the titlers of the foreſaid houſe of Suffolke. But the King of Scotlands right needeth no furtherance by ſtayning of any others birth or honor, by reaſon that the obiections which are made againſt him beeing diſprooued, as eaſilie they may bee, his right by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent of blood can not with anie reaſon or probabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie be brought in queſtion.</p>
            <p>The impediments objected againſt him are in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber three; which (God willing) I will ſufficientlie diſprooue, eſchewing, ſo far as I may, all tediouſnes. The firſt is forrain birth: the ſecond a pretended te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament of King Henrie the eight: the third an acte of aſſociation, alledged to haue bene made in Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament the 27. yeare of her Maieſties reigne.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:174758:5"/>
               <head>THE OBIECTION OF FORRAIN birth is clearlie avoided.</head>
               <p>THE firſt by ſuch as obiect the ſame is groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon an alledged maxime or generall aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion of the common law: which is, that who ſoeuer is borne out of England, and of father &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther not beeing vnder the obedience of the King of England, can not be capable of anie inheritance in England.</p>
               <p>Heereunto I anſwere that this maxime is vntrue in that generall ſenſe: as it appeareth expreſlie by that which is ſet doun by law in the ſeuenth &amp; ninth yeares of King Edward the fowrth, &amp; in the eleuenth and fourteenth of King Henrie the fowrth: That a ſtranger may purchaſe land in England, as alſo that hee may inherite by his wife, if he marie an inhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix.</p>
               <p>But the true maxime or rule againſt the inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of ſtrangers is grounded onelie vpon a ſtatute, made in the 25. yeare of King Edward the third, and is to be reſtrained vnto proper inheritances onlie: to wit, that no perſon borne out of the alleageance of the King of England, whoſe father and mother were not of the ſame alleageance at the time of his birth, ſhal be able to haue, or demand anie heritage with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſame alleageance, as heire to anie perſon.</p>
               <p>Which rule for ſundrie reaſons can not be preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall to the King of Scotlands right.</p>
               <p>Firſt, for that it is a common and generall rule of the Lawe of England, that no rule or maxime of the law, be it neuer ſo generall, can touche or be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood
<pb facs="tcp:174758:6"/>
of matters concerning the croun; except ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe mention be made thereof: and that the croun is priuiledged in manie points aboue private herita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.</p>
               <p>The ſecond reaſon is, for that the demand &amp; title of a croun can not be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehended vnder the words of the foreſaid ſtatute againſt aliens; and that for two reſpects. Firſt, for that the croun can not properlie be called an inheritance of alleageance, or within allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance (as the wordes of the ſaide ſtatute doe ſtand) for that it is not holden of anie ſuperiour, nor with al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leageance, but immediatlie of God: and ſecondly for that the ſtatute meaneth plainlie of inheritance by deſcent; for otherwiſe, as is ſaid, an alien may holde by purchaſe. But the croun is a thing incorporate, &amp; deſcendeth not according to the courſe of other pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate inheritances, but rather goeth by ſucceſſion, as other incorporations doe. In ſigne whereof no King can by law auoyd his letters patents by reaſon of his none-age, as other common heires vnder age do. But he is euer preſumed to be of full age in reſpect of his croun. And as a Parſon, Deane, or other head incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate, though he be an alien, might inherite or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand landes in England for his incorporation, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the former ſtatute: ſo much more the inheritour to the croun, though he bee borne out of the dominion of England, may (notwithſtanding the ſaid ſtatute) ſucceed juſtlie to the kingdome.</p>
               <p>The third reaſon is, that in the ſtatute itſelf ther is expreſſe exceptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Infants du Roy: by which words (according to the vſe of them in the french language wherein this ſtatute is written, as alſo of the word Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beri
<pb facs="tcp:174758:6"/>
in latine) is vnderſtood not onlie the Kings iſſue of the firſt degree, but alſo his ofſpring in other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees following. For otherwiſe this exception would be to no purpoſe; conſidering that according to the words of the ſtatute, Subjects children in the firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, borne out of the Kings alleageance, may haue or demand heritages as heires to their parents, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
               <p>Alſo, the Kings children in the firſt degree needed no ſuch exception, becauſe the words of the ſtatute debarring thoſe that ſhould be borne of parents not being of the Kings alleageance, could no wiſe be pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>judiciall to them, but rather to thoſe of the Kings of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring, who in degrees farther remooued might bee borne in forraine dominions: as ſundrie of king Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the thirds ofſpring were, comming of his ſonns maried in diuers countries: for whoſe behoof eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allie it ſeemeth that this exception was added by him to the former ſtatute.</p>
               <p>And if this exception of infants du Roy be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood onlie in reſpect of priuate heritages, that may fall to them, (in which onlie ſenſe it ſeemeth to haue relation to the words of the ſtatute, making mention of heritages within the kings allegeance) how much more is the priviledge contained therein due to the inheritour of the croun, who by all right and equity may claime a greater praerogatiue in his ſucceſſion to the kingdom, than any other of the kings ofſpring in his priuate inheritance?</p>
               <p>The fourth reaſon is, that ſundrie borne out of the Realme, and of parents that were not of the alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance of England, when they were born, as namely
<pb facs="tcp:174758:7"/>
king Steuen, and king Henrie the ſecond, were ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the croune, without contradiction in reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of their forraine birth. Which argueth that by the common courſe of our old common lawes there was no ſuch ſtop againſt aliens, and that if the ſtatute made in King Edward the thirds dayes, woulde haue derogated or abridged this auncient libertie, it wold haue made ſpeciall mention thereof, which it doeth not.</p>
               <p>The fifth reaſon is the judgement of King Henrie the ſeauenth, and of his counſell concerning this matter.<note place="margin">POLID. VERG. hiſt lib. 26.</note> For, they being in conſultation together a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the mariage of Margaret, the kings eldeſt daugh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, with Iames the fowrth at that time King of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, ſome of them mooued a doubt, to wit, what ſhould enſue, if by chance the Kings iſſue male ſhuld faile, and the ſucceſſion deſcend to the ſaid Marga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret, as it now doth. Whereunto that moſte wiſe and prudent Prince made anſwere; That if ſo it chanced, England, being the cheef and principall parte of the Iland, ſhould thereby receaue no domage, but rather great aduantage; for that it would draw to it ſelf the kingdome of Scotland, as before it had done Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandie, and Aquitaine, with other prouinces: the which anſwere gaue full ſatisfaction and content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the counſell.</p>
               <p>The ſame anſwere alſo, both in reſpect of the truth thereof, and of the perſon that made it, may juſtlie perſwade vs, that the admiſſion of the King of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land to the croun is no wiſe vnlawfull, or prejudiciall to the publique weale.</p>
               <p>But beſides all theſe reaſons ſhowing manifeſtlie,
<pb facs="tcp:174758:7"/>
that neither by anie maxime of the common Lawe, nor by the wordes of the alledged ſtatute, nor yet by the practiſe and cuſtome of our Realme, an alien may bee repelled from ſucceſſion to the kingdome, when by right of blood it falleth to him; there are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther two reaſons, which in particular make for the King of Scotland.</p>
               <p>The one reaſon is, that Scottiſhmen are in our Chronicles accounted as ſubjectes by way of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, howſoeuer they denie it: In reſpect whereof it ſeemeth that the auncient records, making mention of ſeruice to be done within this Iland, containe the frenche words, Dens les quatre mers, or the latine, Infra quatuor maria, within the foure ſeas: in which bounds Scotland being within the North ſea is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed.</p>
               <p>The other reaſon is, that the former ſtatute of king Edward the third is intituled, Of them that are borne beyond the ſeas: and that in the bodie of the ſame ſtatute the doubt is mooued of children borne out of the alleageance of England beyond the ſeas: whereby can not bee vnderſtood Scotland, it being a part of the ſame Iland.</p>
               <p>By all which reaſons the obiection of forraine birth is clearlie and ſufficientlie auoided. Wherefore I go on forward to the confutation of the pretended Teſtament of king Henrie the eight.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:174758:8"/>
               <head>THE OBIECTION OF KING Henries pretended teſtament is confuted.</head>
               <p>IN the 28, and 35. yeares of King Henries raigne, vpon ſome doubt, which then he himſelfe ſeemed to haue about the order of ſucceſſion in his owne children, and for taking away all occaſion of contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie which after his death might ariſe thereupon, the Parliament gaue authoritie to the king to debate and determine that matter himſelf, wirh his learned counſell, who beſt knew the lawes of the Realme, &amp; titles that anie might haue to the croun: and what ſucceſſion he ſhould declare as right &amp; lawful, vnder his letters patents ſealed, or by his laſt will and teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment lawfullie made and ſigned with his own hand, that the ſame ſhould be receaued for good and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. Vpon pretence whereof ſoone after the kings death there was ſhewed a will with the kings ſtamp at the ſame, &amp; the names of diuerſe witneſſes, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſucceſſion of the croun, after his own children, was aſſigned to Ladie Frances, and Ladie Eleonors ſucceſſours, who were neeces to the King by his youngeſt ſiſter. Which aſſignation being, as it were a meere gift made to Frances, and Eleonor in preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of his eldeſt ſiſters right, was founde to bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all law, reaſon, and nature; and therefore not thought to proceed from ſo wiſe a Prince as king Henrie was; but rather forged, and the kings ſtamp ſet to by others, either when he was paſt vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, or after his death. And heereof there want not moſt euident reaſons, and proofes:</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:174758:8"/>Firſt it is not credible that King Henrie would a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt lawe and juſtice diſherite the line of his eldeſt ſiſter, and ſo giue occaſion of ciuill and forrain wars, eſpeciallie ſeing in ſuch a caſe of ſo apparent wrong in ſo great a matter, hee might well fore-ſee, that the authoritie of a Parliament would take little effect a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the true &amp; lawfull inheritour, as appeared not long before in Henrie the ſixt, Edward the fourth, &amp; Richard the third. In whoſe reignes diuerſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie Parliaments made againſt the next inheritour held no longer with anie of them, than while he was able to make his owne part good.</p>
               <p>Secondlie, there be manie incongruities and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignities in the ſaid pretended will, to proceed from ſuch a Prince, as King Henrie was. For, what can be more ridiculous, than to giue the croune to Frances and Eleonors heires, and not to themſelues? And yet by this Teſtament the ſonne of Abraham Stokes (who maried the ſame Frances after the death of her firſt husband the Marques of Dorſet, beeing but her owne ſeruant) ſhould haue claimed before her, if he had had anie by her. Of lyke abſurditie is it, that in the ſame Will the King is ſaide to binde his owne daughters to marie by direction of his counſell, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe to looſe the benefite of ſucceſſion: whereas the daughters of his neeces Frances, and Eleonor, were not bound thereby to anie ſuch conditioun.</p>
               <p>Thirdlie, there bee diuerſe arguments alledged in law, why this Will is not authenticall. Firſt, for that it is not aggreable to the minde and meaning of the Parliament, which intended onlie to giue authoritie for declaration of the true title, and not for donation
<pb facs="tcp:174758:9"/>
or intricating thereof. Alſo, for that there is no law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full or authenticall copie extant of the ſame, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie a bare inrolment in the Chancerie; which is not ſufficient in ſo waightie an affaire: no witneſſe of the priuie counſell, or of the nobilitie to the ſame, which could not haue wanted in ſo great a cauſe (for the beſt of the witneſſes therein named was Sir Iohn Gates, whoſe miſerable death is well knowne:) No publique notarie, nor probation of the will before anie Biſhop, or anie lawfull court appointed for that purpoſe: no examination of the witneſſes, or other things ordinarilie done for lawfull confirming of ſuch a matter. But of all other things this is of moſte importance, that the King neuer ſet his own hand to the foreſaid Will: but his ſtamp was ſet thereto by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, either after his death, or when hee was paſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance: which is confirmed by witneſſes farre more worthie credite, in reſpect of their degree and reputation, than Sir Iohn Gates, &amp; the others whoſe names were ſubſcribed. For firſt the Lord Paget in the beginning of Queene Maries daies, being of her priuie counſell, diſcouered the ſame of his owne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde, and vpon meere motion of conſcience, confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing before the whole counſell, and after before the whole Parliament, how that himſelf was priuie ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, and partly alſo culpable, being drawne thereto through the inſtigation &amp; forcible authoritie of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Alſo Sir Edward Montague, Lord chief juſtice, that had bene preſent and priuie to the ſame doings, and one William Clerk, that put the ſtamp to the pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per, confeſſed the whole premiſſes to be true. Vpon which diſcouerie Queen Marie, &amp; her counſel cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed preſentlie the ſaid inrolment lying in the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerie
<pb facs="tcp:174758:9"/>
to be cancelled, defaced, and aboliſhed.</p>
               <p>And ſince that time in hir Maieſties daies that now liueth, about the 11. or 12. yeare of her reigne, by oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a certain book ſpred abroad at the ſame time verie ſecretlie, for advancing of the houſe of Suffolke by pretence of this Teſtament, the Duke of Norfolk, the Marques of Wincheſter (which then was Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer) the Earls of Arundel, and Pembroke, together with his ſonne, and my Lord of Leceſter, with others met together vpon that matter. And after long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference about the foreſaid pretended Will, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie proofes laid downe why it could not be true; the olde Earle of Pembrok proteſting, that hee was with the King in his chamber from the firſt day of his ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to the laſt houre, and that thereby he could aſſure them this pretended will to be falſe, and counterfait; at length by ſome of them it was mooued, that from that place they ſhould go with the reſt of the Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and proclaime the Scottiſh Queene heire appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent in Cheapſide.</p>
               <p>And albeit, for ſome cauſes to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues beſt known, they proceeded not in publiſhing of the ſame: yet my Lord of Pembrok now liuing can bear witneſſe, that this much is true, &amp; that his father the olde Erle told him openly at that time before the noble men, that he had brought him to that aſſembly, to inſtruct him in the truth, and charged him to witneſſe the ſame, &amp; to defend it alſo with his ſword, if neede required, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his death. The remembrance and due regard of which admonition as yet, no doubt, remaineth in the minde of that noble man.</p>
               <p>All theſe reaſons and proofes being more than
<pb facs="tcp:174758:10"/>
ſufficient to diſproue this pretended Teſtament, I pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceed forward to the confutation of the third and laſt obiection.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>THE ALLEDGED ACT OF ASSO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation is diſprooued; and vpon occaſion offered thereby is declared the great force and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative of right by inheritance to the ſucceſſion of a Kingdome.</head>
               <p>THE third obiection, which is an alledged act of aſſociation, is vrged by a fugitiue and ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous traitour, diſguiſing himſelf vnder the name of Dolman, in a conference which he hath publiſhed touching the Royal ſucceſſion: wherein going about to diſprooue the right and titles of all ſuch as are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract of the blood Royall, ſince King Henrie the ſixt, and to currie fauour with the King of Spain, and the Infanta, by forging them titles and intereſt to the croun of England, he ſheweth himſelf moſt malitious againſt the King of Scotland aboue all others, moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing doubts and ſurmiſes, though full of notorious vanitie and falſhood, to bring his right in queſtion, &amp; to diſgrace his perſon: for that hee is aſſured nothing will ſo much ouerthwart the deſire, and purpoſe, that he, and his like haue of betraying their natiue coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie to the enemies thereof; as the acknowledging &amp; accepting of the King of Scotland for right and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full inheritour to the croun.</p>
               <p>But the onlie obiection which he auoucheth (how ſhameles ſoeuer he be) to be ſuch, as can not be aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, is an act of aſſociation, alledged by him to
<pb facs="tcp:174758:10"/>
haue beene made in Parliament the 27. yeare of her Maieſties reigne, containing theſe words: That who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ſhal be conuinced to conſpire, attempt, or pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cure the death of the Queen, or to be priuie, or acceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie to the ſame, ſhall looſe all right, claime, or actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that the ſame parties, or their heires haue, or may haue to the croun of England. Wherunto he addeth, that vpon this ſtatute the late Queene of Scotland being condemned, and executed by authoritie of the ſaide Parliament, it ſeemeth euident that this King, who pretendeth al his right to the croun of England by his ſaide mother, can haue none at all.</p>
               <p>This is the ſomme of Dolmans obiection: which is clearlie diſprooued by the manifeſt vntruth of that which he alledgeth. For neither any ſuch act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment hath euer bene made, neither alſo is it true that the king hath no other right to the croun of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, than by his mother: for that hee may likewiſe juſtlie claime the ſame by his father, as appeareth manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie by the deſcent of kindred ſet doun in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this treatiſe.</p>
               <p>The ground, whereon Dolman hath deuiſed his forged act of Parliament, was an act or Inſtrument of aſſociation made by ſome Lordes of the counſell not long before the Scottiſh Queens arraignement: wherin were contained certain promiſes to be made for the preſeruation of the Queens Maieſties perſon, by ſuch, as ſhould ſubſcribe therunto. Among which promiſes one is, That they ſhall neuer deſiſt from all maner of forcible purſute, to the vttermoſt extermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of all ſuch perſons, or their abettors, that ſhall by anie act, counſell, or conſent doe anie thing, that
<pb facs="tcp:174758:11"/>
ſhall tend to the harme of her Maieſties Royall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. And if anie ſuch wicked attempt ſhal be taken in hand, or procured, whereby anie that haue, may, or ſhall pretend title to come to the croune by the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timelie death of hir Maieſtie, ſo wickedlie procured, may be advanced: they bind themſelues jointly, and ſeuerallie neuer to accept, allow, or fauour anie ſuch prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded ſucceſſor, by whom, or for whom, any ſuch deteſtable act ſhall be committed, or attempted: or anie that may any way claime by, or from ſuch a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or pretended ſucceſſour.</p>
               <p>This act of aſſociation being ſent throughout the Realme to be with oath ratified and ſubſcribed, was by ſundry men of honourable degree, and good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience thought ſo hard and wrongfull, by reaſon of the clauſe concerning ſuch as might claime by, or from anie perſon culpable of anie attempt againſt her Maieſties perſon, as they refuſed their oathes &amp; ſubſcription therunto.</p>
               <p>Wherevpon the next Parliament following an act was made, limiting and reſtraining this penaltie and excluſion onelie to thoſe pretenders, By whom, or by whoſe meanes, aſſent, or priuitie any inuaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or rebellion ſhall bee had, or made into, or within anie of her Maieſties Realmes or dominions, or any acte attempted tending to the hurt of hir Maieſties Royal perſon, the ſame being firſt denounced by ſuch a nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of perſons, of ſuch eſtate, and in ſuch manner, as is expreſſed in the ſaid act. Wherunto is alſo added, That if any ſuch deteſtable act ſhould be executed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her Maieſties perſon, whereby her life ſhould be taken away, that then euerie ſuch perſon, by, or for
<pb facs="tcp:174758:11"/>
whom any ſuch act ſhould be executed, and their iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſues beeing in anie wiſe aſſenting, or priuie to the ſame, ſhould by vertue of this act be excluded, &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habled for euer to haue, or claime, or to pretend to haue, or claime the croun of this Realme, or anie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther her Maieſties Dominions.</p>
               <p>This act of Parliament, whereby the former act of counſell is limited &amp; reſtrained, no wiſe debarreth the King of Scotland from the croun (as euidentlie appeareth by that part thereof, which I haue rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and by the reſt of the ſame act publiſhed among the other acts of that Parliament) ſeeing he is free, as the world knoweth, from all ſuſpition of anie wicked attempt againſt her Maieſties perſon, and from al co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, or priuitie therunto.</p>
               <p>And trulie it is not credible that her Maieſtie, or the Parliament would go about to debarre him by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch act, as is alledged by Dolman: ſeing they may with reaſon perſwade themſelues, that no ſuch act would ſtay him from claiming, &amp; purſuing his right, nor ſuch as are in England wel affected towards him, (whereof there wanteth not a great nomber of the moſte honorable and beſt ſorte) from aſſiſting and furthering him to the Kingdome.</p>
               <p>The example heerof hath bene ſene not manie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges paſt in ſome of our own Kings, as namelie in Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the fowrth, and Henrie the ſeauenth. For albeit Richard Duke of Yorke,<note place="margin">HOLING. an. 38. HEN, 6.</note> and Edward his ſonne were attainted by act of Parliament, and both they, and their poſteritie to the ninth degree therby excluded from ſucceeding to anie heritage: yet Edward the
<pb facs="tcp:174758:12"/>
fowrth, eſteeming himſelf (as alſo he was accounted by a great part of the realme,) next to the crowne by right of ſucceſſion, wanted neither courage, nor aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to purſue, and win the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">HOLING. an. 2. RICH. 3.</note>Alſo, though Henrie the ſeauenth was attainted by Parliament in King Richards daies: yet at ſuch time as remaining baniſhed in France, he had made a ſolemne oath and promiſe to eſpouſe Ladie Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth, daughter and heire to King Edward the fowrth, offered him in mariage by her Mother the Queene (hauing then with his own claime to the croune ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned alſo the right of the houſe of York) hee was in a maner at the ſame time ſaluted &amp; honoured as King by the Earle of Oxford, and other noble-men, who were there preſent: &amp; comming ſone after into Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land wanted not aſſiſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to depriue the vſurper, king Richard, both of life, and kingdome.</p>
               <p>By which examples it is manifeſt, of how little force is the authoritie of Parliament to exclude a Prince from the right due to him by inheritance, or to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw ſuch as fauour him from giuing him aſſiſtance, or the people from the dutie and alleageance which they owe him. Yea, this right of ſucceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by blood is accounted among al nations, ſubject to this kinde of Monarchie, a thing ſacred, and in no wiſe to be viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. In confirmation whereof I might alledge manie examples of ſundrie forraine kingdomes. But, for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoiding tediouſnes, I will onlie ſet doun heere two ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>amples of the frenche nation; the one verie auncient, the other of our time.</p>
               <p>At ſuch time as the croun of France fell by inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to Charles, for his dulneſſe of wit and want of
<pb facs="tcp:174758:12"/>
iudgement ſurnamed the ſimple; Odo, his kinſman,<note place="margin">PAVL AEMIL. hiſt. FR, in reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no CAR. SIMPL.</note> was declared King, and ruled ouer the greateſt parte of the Kingdome by conſent almoſt of al the Peeres, and principall nobilitie thereof, except the Earle of Flanders, and the Archebiſhop of Rhemes, who did homage to Charles. But Odo, neere the time of his death, approouing the right of his couſen Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, ſpake theſe words to the nobilitie then preſent, as PAVL. AEMYL. rehearſeth them in Latine. CA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ROLVS Balbi filius (id quod jus aequumque poſtulat) Rex vocitetur: á quo amouere jus regni vniuerſus ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarum orbis, ſi conſpiret, non valeat: etiamſi ſceptra manu extorqueat. That is to ſay, Let CRARLES the ſonne of Balbus, according right and equitie, be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led King: from whom all the world, if it ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire againſt him, can not remooue the right of the kingdome, though it ſhould wreſt the ſcepter out of his hand. And as then Odo did acknowledge Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les to be onlie lawfull king: ſo both then, and in al a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges following was he accounted by the frenche nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: whereas Odo is not ſo much as reckoned in the regiſter of the frenche kings.</p>
               <p>Lately alſo it hath bene ſene, that the French king, who now reigneth, albeit after the death of the laſte King his religion was different from the Romane re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, publiklie profeſſed in France: yet was hee fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed and aſſiſted not onelie by the profeſſors of his owne religion, but alſo by al the cheef nobilitie, gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, and beſt part of the people, called Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques; notwithſtanding that the Cardinal of Bour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon, one of the blood Royal, and of their owne Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, was called King by the ſeditious followers of
<pb facs="tcp:174758:13"/>
he League. And at this time he is by al French-me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of whatſoeuer Religion, ackowledged for their onlie lawfull King.</p>
               <p>But in this point our own people hath neuer bene inferiour to the Frenche nation, or anie other: which is made euident by their faithful &amp; dutifull acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of the next lawfull blood ſo manie ages paſt; but eſpeciallie by a moſte notable proofe, which not long ſince they haue giuen of the ſame. For when Lady Iane was by the deuiſe &amp; procurement of ſome noble-men, and Lordes of the counſell proclaimed Queene in London, and other where, the towre bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſurpriſed, and ſundrie other politick meanes vſed for her eſtabliſhing, and for drawing of the people to her obedience: yet was not Queene Marie, the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full inheretrix of the Kingdome, abandoned therfore by the good and faithfull ſubiects thereof, but aſſiſted and furthered by them to the winning and poſſeſſion of the croune: which Ladie Iane loſt togeather with her head: as alſo her father, the Duke of Suffolk; her father in law the Duke of Northumberland, the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour &amp; principall actour of this Tragedie; her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band ſonne to the ſaid Duke, and ſundrie other of her friends, were partakers of her miſerable end, as they had bene of her vnlawfull aduancement.</p>
               <p>By this example may bee euidentlie ſeene, how great is the force of right by inheritance, &amp; how hard it is to draw away the hearts of the people from the lawfull heire, to the acknowledging of anie other. Which being vnderſtood by ſome of our kings, who depoſing, or excluding the lawfull ſucceſſours tooke the croun on themſelues, judged not anie authoritie
<pb facs="tcp:174758:13"/>
of Parliament ſufficient to juſtifie their vſurping, and approoue it to the people; except they had made ſome pretence of a title by right and lawfull inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
               <p>King Henrie the fowrth (who at the houre of his death, ſpeaking to his ſonne,<note place="margin">HOLING. an. 14. HENR. 4.</note> ſeemed to acknowledge his wrongful vſurping) at ſuch time as he took on the croun, albeit he was ſure not to want the authority of Parliaments to eſtabliſh him, yet thought not that ſufficient, except he had laid claime to the crowne, as being by right of inheritance next to the ſame: &amp; that not as heire to his father, Iohn of Gant, or to his grand-father, King Edward the third (for hee knewe that both king Richard, whome he had depoſed, and Roger Mortimer, Earle of Marche, declared alreadie by Parliament heire apparent, were neerer than him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the croun, they being heires to his fathers two elder brethren) but as right and lawful heire to Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie the third: as the verie wordes of the claime,<note place="margin">HOLING. an. 22. RICH. 2. Anno 1, HEN. 4.</note> that he made before a great aſſemblie of the nobilitie, &amp; people do plainlie teſtifie.</p>
               <p>The cauſe heereof was a report made by ſome of his fauourers; to wit, that Edmond, ſonne to Henrie the third, of whome he was deſcended by his mother Blanche, was elder brother to Edward the firſt, but de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>frauded of his right by the ſaid Edward, by reaſon of the deformitie of his crooked back. But this was no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thing elſe, but a fable deuiſed to conueigh to him a title by inheritance. Whereby it appeareth of how great account was the right of inheritance in his judgement, and in the judgement of the people at that time.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:174758:14"/>Alſo Richard the third, who after a farre more wicked maner vſurped the croun,<note place="margin">Sir THO. MOORE in his hiſt. of RICH. the 3.</note> judged not that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie approbation which hee might haue by Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment could ſerue his turne; except he did forge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a title, by deuiſing and publiſhing an vntruth, to his owne mothers infamie: which was, that his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther King Edward was vnlawfullie begotten, and that therefore his children coulde not lawfullie ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to the croun: ſo much did euen that wicked v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurper attribute to the nighneſſe of the right &amp; law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full blood in his owne conſcience.</p>
               <p>And not onelie the example of theſe two Kings, but alſo of all the Princes which we haue had from King Edward the third hitherto (whereof manie are renowmed for their rare wiſdome, and juſtice) ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vs plainlie, in how great regarde we ought juſtly to haue the right of ſucceſſion by the next lawfull blood, in that ſundrie of them haue with armes pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued and maintained their title to the crowne of France, whereof once they had poſſeſſion by right of blood: and none of them hitherto hath forgone their ſaid title, notwithſtanding whatſoeuer frenche Lawes, and acts of Parliament to the contrarie.</p>
               <p>The like alſo hath beene the iudgement of our Parliaments concerning this matter of ſucceſſion, as it hath alwaies appeared by their conſent in appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the title of our Kings to the crowne of France, and by their owne ſtatutes approouing the right of the next lawfull blood to the crowne of England, ſo oft as the ouer great power and authoritie of ſuch as vſurped the Kingdome did not reſtraine their liberty.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:174758:14"/>By all theſe examples alledged by mee appeareth the great prerogatiue, which is due to the next law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full inheritour of the croune. Wherefore I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that as hir Maieſtie, and the Parliament haue not hitherto made anie ſuch act, as is alledged by Dolman, or anie other that might bee prejudiciall to the King of Scotlands title: ſo they wil heerafter rather further him, by declaring him publiklie right &amp; lawful inheritour of the Kingdom, than anie wiſe go about to ſtop or hinder him, not onelie in reſpect of his vndoubted right, and of the prerogatiue and fauour due to the ſame: but alſo for the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold and great benefits which the Realm ſhall receaue by his admiſſion, as by the diſcourſe following ſhal be made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:174758:15"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:174758:15"/>
            <head>A diſcourſe shevving hovv expedient and neceſſarie it is for the Realme of England, that the King of Scotland be in due time acknowledged, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted for lawfulll ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour to her Maieſtie.</head>
            <p>HAuing hitherto ſufficientlie declared the King of Scotlands juſt title to the croune of England, and diſprooued ſuch obiections as are made againſt the ſame, I thought good brieflie to ſhew, how expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient and neceſſarie it is for the weale publike of this Realme, that he be in due time acknowledged, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued for lawfull ſucceſſour to hir Maieſtie.</p>
            <p>To begin therefore with the conſideration of his right, there is no doubt but in reſpect thereof his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion will procure greater peace and quietneſſe to the common wealth, than the vnlawfull intruſion of any other. For all the honeſt and faithfull ſubiects of this Kingdome will in conſcience, and dutie ſubmit themſelues more willinglie to the next lawfull heire, ſucceeding according to the auncient lawes, and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of this countrie, than to another comming to the croune by vnlawfull vſurpation. And ſuch as for their own priuate advantage, or other reſpects would wiſh, and go about to procure the diſturbance of the common wealth, wil haue the leſſe pretence, occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and meanes to effect their wicked deſires and intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the next lawful heire being aduanced. Yea, euen they, who pretend any title to the croun, would be ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perſwaded and content to yeeld to him, than to
<pb facs="tcp:174758:16"/>
anie other of their competitors hauing leſſe right.</p>
            <p>Alſo the preferment of the next lawfull heire, in that he is alreadie a King, wil procure the greater peace &amp; quietnes to the common wealth. For the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlers themſelues, &amp; the reſt of our noble-men (whoſe example and authoritie draweth commonly the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple after them in matters belonging to the Royal ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion) will rather ſubmit themſelues to the next lawfull heire, beeing alreadie a ſoueraigne Prince, than to another not hauing ſo juſt a title, and beeing but of their own rank and degree. And trulie it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooueth them ſo to do: for that if any of themſelues be preferred before the reſt, they may haue the juſter occaſion to feare the jealouſie and ſuſpition of one advanced from the degree of a ſubject to the dignity of a King. The advancement of which kinde of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons hath manie times (as both our own hiſtories, &amp; others teſtifie) procured the deſtruction not onlie of ſuch as reſiſted them; but alſo of thoſe who aſſiſted &amp; furthered them to the croun; yea, and of ſuch of their own blood as they ſuſpected might haue any wiſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed, or endangered their eſtate.</p>
            <p>The trueth heereof is manifeſt by the example of King Edward the fowrth, and Richard the third: who both not onlie deſtroied, and banniſhed their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the houſe of Lancaſter, with their adherents; but alſo the former of them put to death his own bro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, George Duke of Clarence, and the other mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered his young nephues, Edward the fift, and his brother: yea the principal men, who of ſubiects made them Kings, were by them deſtroied, to wit, the Earle of Warwick by King Edward, &amp; the Duke of Buckin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghame
<pb facs="tcp:174758:16"/>
with others by King Richard.</p>
            <p>As the like inconuenience might be juſtly feared, if any of our owne titlers ſhould be preferred before the reſt: ſo there is no meanes ſo effectuall to make ſuch as are of the blood Royall, and the reſte of our nobilitie free from all ſuch dangers, and from all ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition and feare therof, as the preferring of a Prince, whoſe preheminence in dignitie far aboue them, joi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the certaintie of his manifeſt right, and the confidence which he may iuſtlie put in ſo many mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and helpes as hee ſhall haue to aſſure his eſtate, will make him to ſtand the leſſe in jealouſie and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt of others, and conſequently not to vſe thoſe wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked practiſes, which inferiour perſons, raiſed from the degree of ſubiects to the dignitie of Princes, and that by no iuſt title, woulde by all likliehood vſe for their eſtabliſhment. Which inconuenience is ſo much the leſſe to bee feared in the advancement of the preſent King of Scotland; as he hath alreadie giuen ſufficient proof of his tender affection and bountie towardes ſuch as are of his kindred, and of his fauour and cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie towards ſuch of his Nobilitie, as haue not ſhewed themſelues ouer malitious and obſtinate in offending him. How much more then is it iuſtlie to be looked for, that he will ſhew himſelfe thankfull &amp; bountifull towardes all ſuch of our Nobilitie, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good ſubiects, as will highlie deſerue his fauor, in furthering and advancing him to his right?</p>
            <p>But conſidering, beſides his right, his Royall dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie and honorable diſpoſition, that he is alſo King of a country bordering vpon ours, and incloſed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſame Iland, wee muſt iudge his admiſſion alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
<pb facs="tcp:174758:17"/>
neceſſarie; if we deſire our preſent quiet eſtate to be free from danger both inward, &amp; outward. For if anie meanes be vſed to debarre him from his right, that will no doubt breed ciuill diſſenſion, and ſundry factions throughout the Realme, among which hee wil not want his adherents of the beſt &amp; wiſeſt num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: beſides whome, beeing fortified with the power of his owne ſubiects, togeather with the aſſiſtance of his friendes and confederates in France, Germanie, Denmark, and other parts, he will by all likeliehood preuaile againſt his enemies.</p>
            <p>But God forbid this occaſion ſhould bee giuen of making this flouriſhing Realme a praie to forraine nations, eſpeciallie in ſo dangerous a time, when as, beſides the diſeaſes which lurk in the entrals thereof, it is alſo troubled with the rebellion of the Iriſhry in Ireland, and with the feare of the king of Spaine fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring the ſaid rebellion with his aſſiſtance, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring a mightie Armada to inuade vs: beeing em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boldned thereto by hope of finding heere aſſiſtance, by reaſon of the preſent controuerſie concerning the Royall ſucceſſion, and by the incouragement of ſome vnnaturall and ſeditious traitours of our own nation; who deſiring the violent alteration of Religion, and ouerthrow of the preſent eſtate, haue not beene aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to forge him a title to the croun of England, &amp; to publiſh the ſame to the world (as I haue alreadie declared) to egge him on thereby to the inuaſion of their natiue countrie.</p>
            <p>It behooueth therefore all honeſt &amp; faithfull ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects of this Kingdome to bewar, that by reſiſting the right and lawful ſucceſſour, or by not acknowledging
<pb facs="tcp:174758:17"/>
him in due time, they put not themſelues in danger of falling vnder the yoke and tyrannie of mercileſſe Spaniards: who if they haue vſed extreame crueltie againſt the poore ſillie Indians, &amp; others, who neuer offended them, will no doubt vſe far more outrage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous crueltie againſt our nation, by whome they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count themſelues notablie diſhonoured, and diſgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced.</p>
            <p>Neither ought ſuch as among vs profeſſe the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Religion (to whom onely the proſperous ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of Spaniards might ſeeme to be leaſt prejudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all) feed themſelues with anie vaine hope of finding fauor at their hands. For notwithſtanding their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant allurements, and the faire promiſes which they make them for the preſent, in hope of their fauour &amp; aſſiſtance; yet if in the end (which God forbid) they ſhould preuaile, and become conquerours of this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme, after the vtter deſtruction and rooting out of al others profeſſing the Goſpell, they would vſe them nothing the more fauourably for betraying their cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trie. Yea, they would deſpiſe, and handle them the wors therfore: as they did Sir Willia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Stanley; whom, for betraying to them the toune of Dauenter, they thruſt ſhamefullie out of the ſame: and would not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter giue him the credite of any other town, but cauſed him, &amp; his regiment in a ſlauiſh maner to trudge vp and doun the low countries, and to lye both ſummer, and winter in poore and bare Villages, as vnworthie to be placed in anie town. So would they alſo vſe the betrayers of their owne natiue countrie as ſlaues and drudges, and vpon anie occaſion of diſpleaſure, or miſtruſt which they ſhould conceiue againſt them,
<pb facs="tcp:174758:18"/>
deale with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as before they had done with the reſt.</p>
            <p>And trulie the beſt might be looked for would be, the vſing them as ſeruants, the abuſing filthilie of their wiues, and daughters, the thruſting of them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Cornwal, and to the moſt barreine parts of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alm, &amp; the holding of them alwaies vnder the yoke of miſerable bondage. Which hard vſage they might juſtlie feare, taking example by the miſeries and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities, that other nations of their Religion haue ſuffered vnder the tyranny of Spaniards.</p>
            <p>The nobilitie, and people of the lowe countries profeſſing the Romane Religion, as well as others of a different profeſſion, haue had ouer great proofe of their intollerable pride and tyrannie, eſpeciallie at their firſt ariual, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as they made their accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to be maiſters ther without controlment or reſiſtance. The truth heerof is teſtified by the beheading againſt al e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie &amp; juſtice of their chief nobilitie, yea of ſuch as did moſte notable ſeruice to the King of Spaine, as namely of the Countes of Egmond, &amp; Horn; by the powling &amp; pilling of the people by violence and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torſion, by the filthy abuſing of their wiues &amp; daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, by miſuſing of themſelues in a ſlauiſh maner, &amp; by other ſuch their tirannical oppreſſions.</p>
            <p>Their pride &amp; tiranny is alſo cauſe, why the ſtats of Naples, Sicily, and Millain, who ſigh &amp; ſob vnder their hard yoake, would ſhake off the ſame, if they could: &amp; why alſo all other ſtates &amp; Princes of Italie, yea euen the Pope himſelf, ſtand in ſo great feare, &amp; ſuſpition of them, as they doe.</p>
            <p>But I may not paſſe vnder ſilence the example yet freſhlie bleeding of their extreame crueltie againſt the people of Cleueland, a ſtate of the Empyre,
<pb facs="tcp:174758:18"/>
whom hauing bene hitherto their frends and for the moſt part of their owne Religion, they haue vſed, as if they had bene their deadly enemies, and like Turks rather than Chriſtians; for that continuing in their obedience towards the Empyre, and their own law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Prince, they would not become ſlaues to the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious houſe of Auſtria.</p>
            <p>If they haue thus vſed theſe, and ſundrie other na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, their ſubiects, and friends, being of their owne Religion, what better vſage can our profeſſors of the Romane Religion look for at their hands, who can not but be odious to them aboue others, in that they are of a nation aboue all others by them hated and re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>doubted? And how might Engliſh hearts abide the extreame pride, and inſolencie of Spaniards, beeing conquerours; who, before the ſetting forth of the laſt Armada to inuad this land, behaued themſelues moſt proudly and ſcornfullie towards our Engliſh noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of their own Religion, who were their Penſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and as deſirous to conquer England to them as themſelues?</p>
            <p>For at that time the Lord Paget offering to Don Bernardino de Mendoza, (who had bene ſome time Ambaſſadour in the Court of England) the meanes of procuring ſeruice and aſſiſtance in England to the King of Spaine; the ſaid D. Bernardino anſwered him, that the King his Maiſter needed not the ſeruice of Engliſhmen in that enterpriſe, and that hee did of charitie whatſoeuer hee had done for the ſaid Lorde Paget, and other baniſhed Engliſh-men.</p>
            <p>Alſo T. Throckmorton in Bruſſels conferring with Iuan de Laſture, the Kings Treaſurer generall, &amp; ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb facs="tcp:174758:19"/>
that he wondred why the King, hauing ſuch pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces for England, made no more reckoning of ſuch Engliſhmen as followed him, who in regard of their parentage and intelligence might be able to do him great ſeruice, if they were hartned with better vſage, wheras now by reaſon of their pouertie &amp; drouping, they were much diſcouraged: the Treaſurer anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that he was not ignorant of the eſtate and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all ſuch Engliſhmen as followed the king, but for his part (ſwearing a ſpaniſh oath or two) he knew not any of them, in regard of abilitie to doe the King ſeruice, worth the ſtraw that lay vnder his feet.</p>
            <p>Moreouer at the verie time that the Duke of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma lay at Bruges, attending the Spaniſh fleet, and ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>king his preparations for England, when our Engliſh penſioners expected (as by all liklihood they might) to be aboue others honored and aduanced; they wer ſo far deceaued of their expectation, that they were the onlie rejected &amp; contemned ſort of all thoſe that followed the court: all other nations, beſides them, beeing fauoured and releeued with ſome moneths paie.</p>
            <p>And (which is more) whereas they mooued the Duke ſundrie times to knowe his pleaſure, how hee would diſpoſe of them in that enterpriſe, telling him that vpon the wel vſing of them depe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded much mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of importance, as the winning of others of their kindred, acquaintance, and religion, who vpon hope of like good vſage would be able to do great ſeruice at their landing: whereas contrariwiſe ſeeing them come ouer ſo poore in ſhew, without credite, money, or armes, like lackies (for ſo were the words of their
<pb facs="tcp:174758:19"/>
requeſt) it would be a cauſe to diſcourage and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw their minds from the Kings ſeruice; they were by the Duke ſcornfullie and with deriſion rejected: neither did he vouchſafe to giue them anie other an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, than onlie that he would think vpon it. But on the night, in which vpon the hurly burly and rumor of the approching of the Spaniſh navy they thought to imbark, he departed towards Dunkerk, leauing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all behind, as vnworthie to bee called vpon, or taken with him.</p>
            <p>Whereupon the Earle of Weſtmerland, my Lord Paget, and ſundrie of the better ſort made their com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plaint to the Duke of Paſtrana, the King of Spaines baſe ſonne, by whom they were as baſelie and ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie handled as by the other. Which euill intreatie wroght ſo great an apprehenſion in my Lord Paget, that he retired himſelf to Bruſſels: where, what with the conceit of this grief, and what with other acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents he ſhortly ended his life.</p>
            <p>The truth of al this haue I learned of men of good credite and reputation profeſſing the Romane reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, together with much more concerning this pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe; which (for auoiding tediouſneſſe) I omit, the rather, for that I am perſwaded manie of themſelues are alreadie acquainted therewith. Whereby the profeſſours of that religion may perceaue, what fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour they ought to look for at the Spaniards hands, if they ſhould conquer the land: ſeing that they, bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but in a vain hope and conceat of proſperous ſuc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſſe, did ſo deſpiſe the principal Engliſh noble-men and others that were in their company.</p>
            <p>They haue therefore juſt cauſe, as well as al other
<pb facs="tcp:174758:20"/>
Engliſh-men, to feare the tyrannie of Spaniards, and to acknowledge rather the King of Scotland for right &amp; lawfull ſucceſſour to the croun (as no doubt but they knowe him to be) than the King of Spaine, whom they know to haue but a late forged and farre ſought title. Let them call to minde how the moſte honorable and beſt ſort of Frenchemen of their own Religion, after the laſt Kings death, woulde not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge anie other then the King nowe reigning: albeit at that time hee profeſſed a Religion different from theirs, and that there wanted not manie Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the houſe of Bourbon, and of the Romane reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, whom they might haue acknowledged. How much more than ſhould Engliſhmen (howſoever they be affected in religion) acknowledge rather the King of Scotla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, who hath the right of both the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al families of York, &amp; Lancaſter, being a friend to all our nation, and a Prince, at whoſe handes, through their faithful and dutifull behauiour, they may look for grace and fauour, than ſubmit themſelues in a ſlaniſh maner to the King of Spaine, betraying their countrie to the moſt cruell enemies thereof, with ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent and manifeſt danger of incurring ſo manie &amp; greuous calamities, as I haue alreadie rehearſed?</p>
            <p>I need not exhort our own profeſſours of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell not to truſt the Spaniards mercie. I only warne and wiſh them to vſe the right remedy of preuenting the great miſchief, which they haue juſt cauſe to fear if the Spaniards ſhould preuaile. And that is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, than to acknowledge &amp; receiue in due time the King of Scotland for next lawfull ſucceſſour to her Majeſtie. For he being thus acknowledged, the quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell
<pb facs="tcp:174758:20"/>
which the King of Spaine purſueth againſt vs, partly for reuenge of ſuppoſed injuries, and partlie for his pretended title, will be either whollie remoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, or at leaſt wiſe greatlie weakned. For with what pretence of juſtice can he go about to diſpoſſeſſe the King of Scotland of his known right, whom he may not challenge for anie injurie done hitherto by him to his father, or to himſelf? It is very likly alſo that his courage and deſire of inuading vs will be much quai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by this conjunction, whereby hee ſhall perceaue that our power and meanes to defend our ſelues, and offend him, wil be redoubled.</p>
            <p>But if proudly and obſtinatly he will perſiſt in the proſecution of his vniuſt quarrell, the vniuſtneſſe thereof will become more notorious to the world. And not onelie England, and Scotland, but alſo the King of Scotlands confederats and friendes wil with al their power and might ioine togeather, to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand his malice and ambition, and to be auenged of ſo manifeſt an iniurie.</p>
            <p>Beſides theſe commodities, which I haue hitherto rehearſed, our common wealth ſhall receaue ſundry other great benefits by the due acknowledgement, and timelie admiſſion of the King of Scotland. The firſt whereof is, that the dominion and power of the crown of England will bee greatlie increaſed by the ioining therunto of his Kingdome: which diuerſe of our Kings haue endeauored to bring to paſſe as well by mariage vvith the heires of the Kingdome of Scotland, as by other meanes. Neither is it to be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that the honour and dignitie of this realme vvill be thereby anie vviſe empaired, as vvas vvell conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered
<pb facs="tcp:174758:21"/>
and for-ſeene by the moſt noble and wiſe king, Henrie the ſeauenth. For when his eldeſt daughter Lady Margaret was to be maried to Iames the fourth King of Scotland, ſome of his counſell fore-caſting that which might fall out, and ſaying that if his iſſue male failed, the croun might be deuolued to the ſaid Lady Margaret; he moſt wiſely anſwered, that incace any ſuch deuolution ſhould happen, it would be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing prejudiciall to England: for that it beeing the principall and more worthie part of the Iland, would draw Scotland to it, as it did Normandie and Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, with other prouinces, from the time of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt. This was the judgement of that moſt worthie and prudent Prince concerning the conjunction of both countries: wherein without doubt al wiſe men, and ſuch as loue the honour, and publik weale of this Realme will aggree with him. And truely by all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall reaſon it ſeemeth moſt meete, that ſince both countries are but one Iland, they ſhould bee alſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one dominion. Which being brought to paſſe, we ſhall not neede to feare the malice and power of any enemies, be they neuer ſo mightie.</p>
            <p>Another commoditie is the reduction and keping of the Iriſhry vnder the obedience of the croun of England. For either willingly they will ſubmit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to the King of Scotlands authoritie, in reſpect of their auncient friendſhip and often alliance with the Scottiſh nation, and of the ſaid Kings deſcent by blood from their auncient Kings (eſpeciallie ſeeing the offences they haue committed hitherto haue not bene made againſt him) or elſe if vvilfullie and obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natlie they ſhall perſiſt in their rebellion, they may
<pb facs="tcp:174758:21"/>
being of the one ſide aſſaulted with our forces, &amp; of the other by the Scottiſh nation (hardened no leſſe than they are to all kinde of trauaile, and ſuffering) within ſhort time be vtterlie ſubdued.</p>
            <p>Moreouer it will be no ſmall advantage to vs, that the Princes, nobilitie, and people of France, Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, Denmark, and other Chriſtian nations, among whome the King of Scotlands right to the crowne of England is not vnknowne, will approue our vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and juſtice in this point, and be the more wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and ready to maintain friendſhip, entercourſe, &amp; traffick with vs: whereas refuſing the King of Scotla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d his right, we ſhould procure their hatred and enemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie againſt vs, with the danger of forraine inuaſion, &amp; of beeing made a praie to ſtrangers, as before I haue declared.</p>
            <p>It is alſo a ſingular benefit offred vs by God, that the Prince, who is to ſucceed in the Kingdome, hath iſſue likewiſe to ſucceed him: ſo as we need not feare new diſturbance of the common wealth for the vncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of ſucceſſion after his reigne. For he hath alreadie three children, whereof the Prince, which is the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, being paſt fiue yeares, is of ſuch towardneſſe, as great expectation may be juſtlie had of him.</p>
            <p>Since therefore the willing admiſſion of the King of Scotland in due time, will procure ſo manie and great commodities to this realme; as alſo the with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding him in his juſte cauſe ſo great inconuenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and dangers, as I haue hitherto declared: truelie they are to be condemned of extreme follie &amp; mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, who being caried away with vain conceits, and
<pb facs="tcp:174758:22"/>
with the remmbrance of olde quarrels, which haue bene betwixt both countries, wil repine &amp; grudge at the advancement of the King of Scotland, ſo juſt, and neceſſarie for our common wealth. As theſe men remember olde quarrels; ſo would I wiſh them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber that there hath bene alſo ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t friendſhip be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>twixt both nations, &amp; eſpecially betwixt their kings, as the often alliance made betweene them doth wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>For beſids alliances made before the conqueſt, Iane, King Iohns daughter, was maried to Alexander, King of Scotland; Margaret, the daughter of his next ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſour Henry the third, to an other Alexander; Iane, daughter of Edward the ſecond, to King Dauid, Iane, daughter to Iohn Duke of Somerſet, grandfather to Henrie the ſeauenth, was maried to Iames the firſt: &amp; laſtly Margaret, eldeſt daughter of King Henrie the ſeauenth, to King Iames the fowrth. This often alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance ſheweth that there hath beene olde friendſhip betuixt the Kings of both nations, though interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from time to time with quarrels and warres: the principall cauſe wherof hauing bene the diuiſion of this Iland into diuerſe kingdomes, the vniting ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of vnder one dominion, will (out of all doubt) be the only meanes to procure peace and concord betwixt all the inhabitants thereof.</p>
            <p>Which vnion as it hath beene ſought heretofore, though in vain, by ſundrie of our own Kings with no ſmall endeauour, and trauaile, as namely by Edward the firſt, Edward the ſecond, and not long ſince by Ed<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward the ſixt: ſo now a fit occaſion is offered of bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:174758:22"/>
the ſame to paſſe, at ſuch time as both nations, by the continuance of peace and amitie, which hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained betwixt them theſe fiftie yeares paſt, and by their agrement in Religion, may bee eaſily linked in perpetuall vnitie and concorde.</p>
            <p>Neither is it anie ſuch inconuenience as ſome me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> imagine, that the Prince, who is to reigne ouer both nations, is not born in England, conſidering that he is ſo manie waies extract, and that by father, as wel as by mother, of the blood Royall of England, and that he hath bene alwaies, and continueth yet a ſure and faithful friend to our eſtate, as his behauiour towards the ſame doth well declare. For hauing bene inuited by ſundrie fair promiſes, and large offers made him by our moſt hatefull and mightie enemies, and ſolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited by ſome of his owne ſubjects, vpon injuries, as they alledged, done him, to break of friendſhip with vs, yet his conſtant affection towardes our common wealth could neuer be altered.</p>
            <p>What deſire he hath alwaies had of keeping our frontiers from all annoiance, no leſſe than his own, it is well ynough knowne by his continual carefulneſſe concerning this point, and eſpeciallie by his ſending not long ſince into our countrie, for pledges of good order to be kept on his part, the LL. of Bacleuch, &amp; Cesford, Wardens of the Scottiſh marches.</p>
            <p>His patience alſo in waiting for the time appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by God, and not attempting ought, vvhich might be any vviſe prejudicial to the perſon or eſtate of our ſoueraigne Lady (a rare example of patience and moderation in ſuch as are to ſucceed to a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome)
<pb facs="tcp:174758:23"/>
may be to vs a ſufficient warrant of his hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable diſpoſition, and conſtant affection tovvards hir Maieſtie, and the common wealth. Wherewith are joyned manie other vertues, and princelie qualities, that may juſtlie mooue vs not onlie to admit him, but alſo to inuite him to the ſucceſſion of the Kingdome: as his pietie and ſinceritie in Religion; his magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie voide of ambition; his good inclination to juſtice, tempered with clemencie; his temperate minde and behauiour, not ſtained with anie ſpot of filthie luſt or ſenſualitie; his princelie liberalitie, &amp; yet no powling or pilling of his ſubjects for entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nement thereof; his extraordinarie painfulneſſe, and great dexteritie in reforming the diſorders of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme, notwithſtanding ſundrie difficulties and impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments which are in this reformation.</p>
            <p>Beſides which, and other princelie vertues where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he is indued, when he ſhall haue the manifolde &amp; great advantages, that the Monarche of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome hath aboue other Princes (as the aſſiſtance of his obedient and dutifull Nobilitie, the ſage adviſe of moſte wiſe and expert Counſellours, the godlie exhortations of the learned Cleargie, procuring o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to the Prince and his Lawes, the help and furtherance of faithfull Iudges, carefull Officers, and other good ſubiects to the execution of his Lawes &amp; commandements, and finally the dutifull and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent affection of the people towardes their Prince) there is no doubt but by his meanes this Kingdome ſhall flouriſh in continuall peace, with all encreaſe of honour and proſperitie.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:174758:23"/>To conclude therefore, ſince by the prouidence of God this worthie Prince is offered to vs, whoſe title is ſo juſt, whoſe admiſſion is ſo expedient and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie, whoſe perſon ought to be ſo acceptable to vs for his good deſerts, and Princelie vertues: I hope that all good and faithfull ſubiects of all eſtates within this Realme will in due time willinglie admit and receaue him to the ſucceſſion of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
